欢迎爱好者加入我们  www.YYeTs.net
Dad?
Clear the ramp! 30 seconds! May God be with you!
Port side and starboard side stick!Move fast and clear those mortar holes!
I want to see plenty of beach between men.
Five men is a juicy opportunity. One man is a waste of ammo.
Keep the sand out of your weapons! Keep those actions clear!
I'll see you on the beach!
Clear the mortar hole! Right and left!
Over the side!
Port and starboard!
Thank yo...
What now, sir?
I said, 'What the hell do we do now, sir?"
Captain Miller! Captain Miller!
Captain Miller! Sergeant Horvath!
Move your men off the beach! Now!
Okay, you guys, get on my ass! Follow me!
-Sir! What's the rallying point?  -Anywhere but here!
-What now, sir?  -The seawall, move up to the seawall!
-Sir, I'm staying!   -Clear the beach to make way.
This is all we've got between us and the Almighty.
Every inch of this beach has been pre-sighted.
You stay here, you're dead men!
Mama, Mama!
Stay down, stay down!
-What are you guys?   -104th Medical Battalion,sir.
-We're here to set up field operations.  -Get rid of that crap!
Grab yourselves some weapons and follow me.
-I'm hit!  -Briggs!
Medic!
-I'm hit low! God!  -Medic!
Navy Beach Battalion, sir!
I've got to clear these obstacles. Make holes for the tanks!
-All the armour is floundering at sea.  -Orders, sir!
Go somewhere else! I'm clearing this one.
Come on, Briggs!
Medic!
Move, move!
Come on, move!
Shore party! No armour has made it ashore.
We've got no DD tanks on the beach.Dog One is not open!
Who's in command here?
You are, sir!
Sergeant Horvath? Do you recognize where we are?
Where we're supposed to be, but no one else is.
Nobody's where they're supposed to be!
Shore party!
First wave ineffective! We do not hold the beach.
Say again, we do not hold the beach!
We're mixed up! We've got people from Fox,Able and George companies.
Plus, we got some Navy demo guys and a beachmaster.
Shore party, Shore party!
CAT-F, CAT-F, CA...
-Reiben here.  -Seen anybody else?
-Jackson,but that's it.  -Mellish here!
Caparzo! We've got DeForest back there with Wade!
D.'s hurt so bad he's sprung a hundred leaks! Wade says he's used up!
-Move on to somebody you can help.  -Let go, he's a battalion surgeon!
-Get his attention!   -Wade!
Wade! Wade!
Wade, don't do it! It's too risky, too risky, Doc!
Get your ass back here!
Get him off the beach.
I've got it! We've stopped the bleeding!
Fuck!
Just give us a fucking chance, you son of a bitch!
Wade, come on! You son of a fucking cocksucker!
Wade, it's Mellish. Wade!
Let's move! We found Miller! Let's move!
Fuck it!
Get down, get down!
This is all? This is all that's made it?
We got scattered pretty bad. There's bound to be more of us.
It's not enough.
Dog One exit. It's the cut to the right, or was it left?
No. Vierville is to the left. This is Dog One.
They're killing us and we don't have a fucking chance! That ain't fair!
-Gather weapons and ammo!  -Gather weapons and ammo!
Reiben! Where's your BAR?
Bottom of the Channel. The bitch tried to drown me.
Find a replacement.
Bangalores! Bring out some bangalores!
Engineers coming! Grenades, give me grenades!
Bangalores up the line! Bangalores up the line!
Heads up! Bangers coming your way! Come on, come on!
-Jackson here, sir!  -Reiben back, sir.
Oh, my God!
Mortars incoming!
One more, give me one more!
Oh, my God, it hurts! I'm going to die!
Oh, my God! Jesus! Oh, my God!
Come on, put it in. Keep it moving.
We've got it.
Jesus! Lucky bastard.
Move it! Keep it moving!
You're not going to die. You're fine. Just don't look at it. Don't look at it!
Bangalores! Clear the shingle!
Fire in the hole! Fire in the hole!
Fire in the hole!
We're in business! Defilade! Other side of the hole!
Give him some morphine.
That's it, let's go.
Inspected, morphine.
Routine.
Priority.
He is gone
Son of a bitch! Get in there.
-Fuck,I can't move!   -Mellish,give me your bayonet.
Sarge.
Two MG-42s, two mortars. Add 20, left 30.
There's defilade, but it's a good firing position if we can land the armour.
We've got to get this draw open!
-Reiben, Mellish! Let's get in the war!  -Take cover and put fire on that crew.
Davis, DeBernardo, Young, Valk! Get ready!
Covering fire!
Go, go, go!
It's a goddam firing squad.
It's the only way we can get everybody out of here.
Short, Payton, McDonald, Parkes! You're next!
Why not just hand out blindfolds, Captain?
All we can do here is die! Covering fire!
Go, go, go!
Come on, come on, come on! Go, God damm it!
-Jackson.  -Sir.
See that impact crater? should give you defilade from the machine gun position.
Get in there and give me some fire discipline. Wait for my command.
Go!
If your mother saw you do that, she'd be very upset.
I thought you were my mother.
Be not Thou far from me, O Lord.
Oh, my God. I am heartily sorry for having offended Thee.
I detest my sins for having offended Thee, O Lord. Listen to me, Lord.
All my strength! Haste Thee to help me.
Dog One exit, right here!
We're in business!
Move, move!
Reiben. Go, Sarge!
Reiben!
Come on, Doyle!
Sarge!
Flame! Doyle, do it!
Don't shoot! Let them burn!
On the right!
I'll give you "comrade", you son of a bitch!
Look out! Turn around, turn around.
Flush them out!
Cease fire, cease fire! Cut it out, cut it out!
Cease fire!
Sugar Cane, Sugar Charlie Three. Say again, Dog One is open.
Send in the dozers. I'm waiting here to tie in my flanks.
What?
What? I'm sorry, I can't understand what you're saying!
What did he say, what did he say?
Look, I washed for supper!
Who's got a bazooka,Goddammit
Hey, Fish. Look at this, a Hitler Youth knife.
And now it's a Shabbat challah cutter, right?
Keep it moving!
That's quite a view.
Yes, it is.
Quite a view.
"Dear Mr Brian Boyd. No doubt by now you have received full information"-
"about the untimely death of your son."
"No words can ever relieve your grief."
"Our outfiit has felt his loss greatly..." "He was a fiine soldier"-
"and believed strongly in what we were doing..."
"We were involved in one of the most important operations of the war."
"Al was the one who held us all together."
"He was the first to volunteer."
"We passed a road where over 4,000 troops had passed."
"Your husband served in a unit whose duty is to place itself beyond..."
"...which we all cherish and hold dear..."
"The loss of Lee and others like him is a distinct blow to the regiment."
"We understand your desire to learn about"-
"the circumstances leading to his death."
Colonel, I've got something you should know about.
These two men died in Normandy.
-This one at Omaha Beach.  -"Sean Ryan."
-This man at Utah.  -"Peter Ryan."
This man was killed last week in New Guinea.
"Daniel Ryan."
The three men're brothers,sir.
I just learned that this afternoon their mother's going to get all three telegrams.
There's also a fourth brother who parachuted in with 101st Airborne -
the night before the invasion. He is somewhere in Normandy.
-Is he alive?   -We don't know.
Come with me.
Goddammit.
All four were in the same company in the 29th Division -
but we split them up after the Sullivan brothers died on the Juneau.
Any contact with the fourth son, James?
No. He was dropped 15 miles inland near Neuville, behind German lines.
Mac, there is no way you can know where he was dropped.
First report from lke's people at SHAEF said the 101st is scattered.
There are misdrops all over Normandy.
Assuming Private Ryan even survived the jump, he could be anywhere.
In fact, he's probably K.I.A.
And frankly, if we go sending some sort of rescue mission, -
flat-hatting throughout German reinforcements along our advance, -
they're going to be K.I.A., too.
I have a letter here...
...written a long time ago to a Mrs Bixby in Boston. So bear with me.
"Dear Madam."
"I have been shown in the files of the War Department a statement" -
"of the Adjutant General of Massachusetts" -
'that you are the mother of five..."
"...sons who have died gloriously on the field of battle."
"I feel how weak and fruitless must be any words of mine" -
'that would attempt to beguile you from the grief' -
"of a loss so overwhelming..."
"...but I can't refrain from tendering the consolation that may be found" -
"in the thanks of the republic they died to save."
"May our Heavenly Father assuage the anguish of your bereavement" -
"and leave you only the cherished memory of the loved and lost" -
"and the solemn pride that must be yours to have laid such a sacrifice" -
"upon the altar of freedom. Yours very sincerely and respectfully," -
"Abraham Lincoln."
That boy is alive. We are going to send somebody to find him.
And we are going to get him the hell out of there.
The Quartermaster's up the beach a way. Look for a blown-up bunker.
-Miller,Charlie Company.  -Go on in,Captain.
If we don't off-load the Shermans by 0600 -
we'll have a division stuck at Carentan with its pants around its ankles.
Well, you let me know of it.
Let Charlie Company hold at Vierville 'til we can get the armour there.
Runner!
Airborne was supposed to win an open door for us, but misdropped, -
and scattered all their sticks into the wind. What's your situation?
Yes, sir... Sector Four is secure.
We took out towed 88s here, here and here.
They got four Shermans and some deuce-and-a-halves.
These two minefields are actually one big one.
We went up the middle of it, but it turned into a mixed high-density field.
A little bit of everything; Sprengmine 44s, Schumne 42s, -
pot mines, A-200s, the little wooden bastard the detectors don't pick up.
Here, they placed big mushrooms, Teller mine 43s, I guess for our tanks, -
from here right up to the edge of the village, right here.
We marked them and called the engineers.
-Resistance?  -We had higher support expectations.
There was a company without artillery. Wehrmacht. 346th Infantry.
Von Lucke Kampfgruppe. We ended up with 23 prisoners.
We turned them over to MPs from the 29th.
What about our casualties?
Well, the figure is... We're 35 dead, times two wounded.
They just didn't want to give up those 88s.
It was a tough assignment. That was why you got it.
Yes, sir.
John...
-I've got another one for you.   -Yes, sir.
It's straight from the top.
I wish. You and I are taking a squad to Neuville on a PR mission.
Oh, are you leading a squad?
A private in the 101st lost three brothers and he's got a ticket home.
-Why Neuville?  -They think he's there.
Part of all those Airborne misdrops.
It won't be easy finding one soldier in the middle of this goddam war.
Like finding a needle in a stack of needles.
What about the company?
We take the pick of the litter, the rest goes to Baker.
Jesus Christ! They took away your company?
It wasn't mine, it was the Army's. So they told me, anyway.
Get me Reiben on BAR, Jackson, Wade, Beasley and Caparzo.
-Beasley's dead.  -Alright,Mellish then.
-Do have a guy who speaks French?    -Not that I know of.
What about Talbot? This morning.
I'm going to try and dig up another interpreter.
Assemble at the battalion motor pool on the beach.
What are we going to do? Listen up. What?
Go home wrapped in the American flag with a hunk of cheese in your ass.
I thought you liked it in the ass. What?
Attention!
As you were. I'm looking for Corporal Timothy Upham.
Yes, I'm Upham.
-Do you speak French and German?    -Yes, sir.
-How's your accent?   -Slight one in French.
-My German's clean.    -Very good.
You've been re-assigned to me. Grab your gear, we're going to Neuville.
-When was this updated?    -As of 8:30 this morning.
This is the 12th SS Panzer. These are the two axes advancing south.
There are Germans in Neuville. I understand, Corporal.
There are a lot of Germans in Neuville. You've got a problem with that?
Please consider that I've never been in combat. I make maps and translate.
I need someone who speaks French and German.
My two guys were killed. I haven't held a weapon since training.
Did you fire the weapon in Basic training?
-Yes, sir.   -Well, then get your gear.
Sir, may I bring...
May I bring my typewriter, sir?
Yes, sir.
Thank you very much.
-Is that a souvenir?    -No, sir.
Take your time.
You should look on the bright side of things, Corporal.
-Yes. -For one thing, you don't need those.
-You'll need that.   -Yes. I'll need this, not that.
Hey! Hey!
You want your head blown off?
Don't touch me with those rat claws again. Get the fuck back in formation!
I was just wondering where you're from.
-Caparzo,is it?  -Drop dead,Corporal.
Gotcha.
Every time you salute the Captain,you make him a target for the Germans.
-I'm sorry.  -Do us a favour.Don't do it.
Especially when I'm standing next to him.Capisci?
-Capisco.  -Corporal,what's your book about?
Watch your rifle. Sorry.
It's about the brotherhood that develops between soldiers during war.
Brotherhood? What do you know about brotherhood?
Get a load of this guy, Fish.
Why don't you ask the Captain where he's from?
Ask the Captain. He'll tell you everything you want to know about him.
Explain the maths of this to me.
Where is the sense in risking the lives of the eight of us to save one guy?
20 degrees. Anybody wants to answer that?
Reiben, think about the poor bastard's mother.
Hey, Doc, I've got a mother.
You've got a mother, Sarge has got a mother.
Shit, I bet even the Captain's got a mother.
Maybe not the Captain, but the rest of us.
"Their's is not to reason why their's is but to do and die"
What the fuck is that supposed to mean, Corporal?
We're all supposed to die?
-Upham's talking about our duty.  -Yes, sir.
We all have orders to follow.
Yes, sir. Thank you. Even if the mission is "FUBAR"?
Especially if the mission is "FUBAR".
-What's "FUBAR"?  -It's German.
Never heard of that...
Sir, I have an opinion on this matter.
By all means, share it with the squad.
From my way of thinking, -
this mission is a misallocation of valuable military resources.
Yeah? Go on.
It seems to me that God gave me a sepcial gift made me a fine instrument of warfare.
Reiben,pay attention.Now, this is the way to gripe.Continue,Jackson.
If He was to put me and this sniper rifle anywhere up to and including -
one mile of Adolf Hitler with a clear line of sight, sir...
Pack your bags, fellas, the war is over. Amen.
That's brilliant, bumpkin.
What about you, Captain? You don't gripe at all?
I don't gripe to you. I'm a captain. There's a chain of command.
Gripe always go up.
You gripe to me, I gripe to my superior officers, and so on.
I don't gripe in front of you. You should know that as a Ranger.
I'm sorry, but let's say that you weren't a captain or that I was a major.
What would you say?
In that case, I'd say, "This is an excellent mission" -
"with a valuable objective worthy of my best efforts."
"Moreover, I feel heartfelt sorrow for the mother of Private Ryan" -
"and I'll lay down my life and those of my men, especially yours, Reiben," -
'to ease her suffering."
He's good. I love him.
Fine!
-Thunder!  -Flash!
Upham, over there. Reiben, you four go.
Go, go, go, go!
You are a sight for sore eyes. Sergeant Hill, our reliefs showed up.
-How many are you?   -Eight. We're not your relief.
What do you mean, sir? We're here for a Private Ryan.
Who? Ryan? What for?
-Is he here?  -Maybe on the other side of the town.
It's hard to get to. The Germans punched a hole in our centre.
-They cut us right in two.  -What's his name,again?
Ryan, James Ryan. He dropped in with the 101st.
Goldman, get me a runner! Runner!
Come on!
Jonesy, make a hole up there!
We got stopped by fire from the eastward.
The Germans have been reinforcing two regiments all day.
It's been quiet for 45 minutes.
The Germans concentrate their fire westward.
Who's that on the loudspeaker? Dagwood Duesseldorf.
Our friendly neighbourhood morale officer.
"The Statue of Liberty is kaput."
That's disconcerting.
Your father was circumcised by my rabbi, you prick!
Cover!
Go!
You sadistic fucking animals! Get down.
They know we're not in direct contact. They'll single out the runners.
Why do they shoot them up?
As long as his lungs are working, he carries the message. We'd do the same.
No, we wouldn't! Wade! Get them ready to travel.
Boyd! Come on!
Try again! Let Captain Hamill know we're coming.
What's the rest of Neuville like?
The next block's got two-storey buildings. A lot of windows.
There's a square with good cover.
Show me. Sarge, hold right here!
Yes, sir!
Stay out of this enfilade and use the buildings.
Try a left hook. Shoot and scoot. Two of yours, two of mine.
Hastings, Goldman! Up front!
Reiben, Caparzo. They're still jamming us.
Short runs, high and low at the corners. It's going to be tight.
Be prepared for close contact. Go.
Upham! You stay with Sergeant Horvath.
Stay here! I'll wear him like underwear, Captain. You stay with me.
Past the end of the block are the gates of the square.
Good. Alright.
Reiben, where's the Captain from?
If you figure it out, you'll get a prize. 300 bucks, last I heard.
The company's got a pool. Five bucks gets you in.
It's around this corner. Defilade right up to those gates.
Somebody must know where he's from.
I've been with him since Casserene Pass. I don't have a clue.
My ankles are killing me. I'll need a wheelchair before the war is over.
That's it! Oh, my God! That ankle is like an old woman.
Like an old... Oh, God!
Reiben. So you don't even know where he went to school?
He didn't go to school. They assembled him at OCS out of dead Gls.
Pay attention to detail. I know where he's from and what he did -
because I pay attention to detail.
Hey, Upham! Careful you don't step in the bullshit.
Do it. Thunder!
Thunder, or we will fire on you!
Mellish, Caparzo, come here!
Tell them to show themselves.
Ask them where the Germans are.
What is he saying? Something about the children.
Kids? He wants us to take them.
No, no. We can't take the kids.
We can't take the kids! No, no!
They think they'll be safe. They won't be safe with us!
Are you nuts? Listen to the Captain!
They think they'll be safe with us.
It's not safe anywhere. Caparzo! Put that kid back!
Caparzo, put the girl back! It's OK, it's OK.
Give that kid back!
Upham, how do you say, "It's OK?" I can't. She reminds me of my niece.
Get the kid back up there!
We should at least take her to the next town.
We're not here to do that, we're here to follow orders!
Sarge, take this goddam kid!
Cover, cover!
No!
Goddammit! Where did that come from?
He was on the ground before we heard the shot.
That's where I'd be.
I didn't see it. 450 yards, maybe a shade under.
I wouldn't venture out there, fellas. This sniper's got talent!
Please don't cry. I'll take you back to Mama and Papa. Please don't cry.
Come on.
Carpy!
Captain! Hold on, Caparzo.
Help me up. I can walk.
Caparzo, stay still!
Two clicks. Left wind.
Fish!
Captain, can you see him? How is he?
Wade, you stay put.
Where is he shot, Captain?
Can you see him? You stay there!
Damn it! Stay down!
What's the matter with you? Am I going to take care of you if you get hit?
Fish, come over here!
Carpy, put your head down! Why can't you put your head down?
Oh, my God, I trust in Thee.
Let me not be ashamed. Let not my enemies triumph over me.
Copy it. Copy it and send it for me.
You're going to send it yourself. Put it down!
-It's got blood on it!   -I see it.
It's... It's to my dad. It's got blood on it, Fish.
We got him. Stay down.
How bad is it? Chest, maybe lung shot.
Get that.30 up the street!
Detail! Clear, up!
Clear, down!
That's why we can't take children.
Sergeant Horvath, do an ammo check.
Upham, canteens. Fill them up.
-Sergeant Hill.   -Yes, sir.
Gather your men. We'll form up at the northwest corner of the square.
-Jackson.   -Sir!
Mellish. Check the tower, hustle back here. Right now, go!
Fuck Ryan!
Thunder! Flash! Come on in!
Hey, guys. We're looking for Captain Hamill.
Down there, across the square. Across the square.
Go easy. Watch for snipers.
Sit down.
Jimmy T. Go and find Captain Hamill. Bring him here.
-What? Up there?   -How should I know? Go and look!
Thank you, you moron.
Alright. You guys just flake out here for a while.
Let me get this goddam hitchhiker out of my boot.
Put your weapons down! Drop them now!
I'll shoot you!
Drop, drop 'em!
Put 'em down!
Clear, up!
Shit, shit!
Clear, down!
Enough to make you old.
Let's hope so.
Hamill, Pathfinders 101st. Miller, 2nd Rangers.
Thank you.
We're looking for a Private Ryan. He's part of your outfit.
Any chance that you policed him up?
How was the road in? Scenic. We lost most of our ammo.
Not to mention one of our men.
Lieutenant! Redeploy that bazooka to the right side of the road.
And get Ryan up here!
Ryan! Ryan! Front and centre! Ryan!
Here comes our boy.
I told you he was an asshole.
Private Ryan reporting as ordered. At ease.
Captain Miller, 2nd Rangers, wants a word with you.
This way.
Alright. Take a knee.
Private, I'm afraid I have some bad news for you.
Well, there isn't any really easy way to say this, so...
...so I'll just say it. Your brothers are dead.
We have orders to come and get you...
...because you're going home.
Oh, my God! My brothers are dead!
I was going to take them fishing when we got home.
I'm so sorry, James. I can't tell you how much.
-How did they die?   -They were killed in action.
That can't be.
They can't be my brothers. They're still in grammar school.
-You're James Ryan?   -Yeah.
James Francis Ryan from lowa?
James Frederick Ryan, Minnesota.
-Does that mean my brothers are OK?   -Yeah,I'm sure they're fine.
Are you sure? We're looking for a different Ryan.
It's just a big foul-up.
How can you be sure? How do you know that the foul-up isn't -
that his brothers are OK, and...
Lieutenant. I'm sorry for the trouble.
I just wrote them a letter before I left. I've got to get home.
I've got to get home right now. I want to go home.
Where is our Ryan? Don't know.
Are you in touch with your CO? What unit's Ryan in?
Baker Company, 506th. The guy with the broken foot's in 506th.
-Charlie, I think.   -You think?
Ryan? Don't know... Man!
-Where was your dropzone?    -Vierville.
Vierville? How did you end up here?
You got me, sir. The C-47 took heavy fire.
Pilot went crazy turning every which way.
We took more fire in the drop. It got messy. I ended up here.
I haven't seen a single guy from my stick. God knows where they are.
Did anybody from Baker Company talk about where the dropzone was?
No, but they had the same rallying point as us.
Show me.
My men are beat. We'll hold up here for three hours and pull out after dark.
Got anything left in this town, like a three-star hotel?
Something with clean sheets, soft pillows and room service?
-How about a nice, comfy church? -We'll take that.
What have you heard? How is it all falling together?
We got the beachhead secured,but Monty's taking his time moving on Caen.
-We can't pull out'til he's ready,so...  -That guy's overrated.
-No argument here.  -You take Caen to take Saint-L8.
-You gotta take St-L8 to take Valognes. -Valognes,you've got Cherbourg.
-Cherbourg,you've got Paris.  -Paris,you've got Berlin.
And then that big boat home.
I could really use you around here, but I understand what you're doing.
-You do?  -I've got a couple of brothers myself.
Oh. Good luck.
-Thank you.   -No, I mean it.
Find him. Get him home.
What's with your hand?
I don't know.
It started in Portsmouth when we went down for embarkation.
-It comes and goes.  -You have to find yourself a new job.
This one doesn't seem to agree with you any more.
What?
-What?   -Nothing.
What was the name of that kid at Anzio?
The one who walked on his hands -
and was singing that song about the man on the flying trapeze?
Vecchio. Vecchio!
Yeah, Vecchio. He was a goofy kid.
I remember he used to pee a "v" on everybody's jackets. For "vecchio".
For victory. Vecchio.
He was so short. He was a midget, wasn't he?
Yeah, how did he get to be a Ranger?
He got shot in the foot once, walking on his hands.
He could walk faster on his hands.
He could run faster on his hands.
Vecchio. Yeah.
Caparzo.
You see, when you end up killing one of your men, -
you tell yourself it happened so you could save the lives of -
two, three, or ten others.
Maybe 100 others.
Do you know how many men I've lost under my command?
-How many?  -94.
But that means I've saved the lives of ten times that many, doesn't it?
Maybe even 20, right? 20 times as many?
And that's how simple it is.
That's how you rationalise making the choice -
between the mission and the men.
Except that this time the mission is a man.
This Ryan had better be worth it.
He'd better go home and cure some disease -
or invent a longer-lasting light-bulb or something.
For the truth is that I wouldn't trade ten Ryans for one Vecchio or Caparzo.
Amen.
Look, there it goes again. Sir.
Are you alright?
We'll move out in two hours. Why don't you get some sleep?
-I don't know how he does it.  -What's that?
Falls asleep like that. Look at him.
The guy's lights-out the minute his head hits the pack.
-Clear conscience.  -What's that saying?
God's on our side, who could be on theirs?
"If God be for us, who could be against us?"
Yeah, what did I say?
The trick to falling asleep is trying to stay awake.
How is that, Wade?
When my mother was an intern she used to work through the night -
and sleep through the day.
The only time we talked was when she'd get home.
I used to lie in bed and stay awake as long as I could,but it never worked
because the harder I tried the faster I'd fall asleep.
That wouldn't have mattered in my house.Ma would've come home,
shook me awake,chatted me up 'til dawn.She was never too tired to talk.
That's probably the only time she could get a word in.
Funny thing is,sometimes she would come home early
and I'd pretend to be asleep.
-Who, your mum?  -Yeah.
She'd stand in the doorway looking at me,
and I would just keep my eyes shut.
And I knew that she just wanted to find out about my day,
that she came home early just to talk to me.
And I still wouldn't move. I'd still pretend to be asleep.
I don't know why I did that.
We've only got a couple of hours. Shut up and go to sleep.
Captain? Sir?
Corporal.
How are you doing? Are you alright?
Yeah, I think this is all good for me, sir.
Really? How is that?
'War educates the senses, calls into action the will," -
"perfects the physical constitution," -
"brings men in such swift and close collision in critical moments," -
'that man measures man."
I guess that's Emerson's way of finding the bright side.
-You know Emerson, sir?   -I know some.
So, where are you from, Captain? What did you do before the war?
What's the pool up to?
I think it's around 300, sir.
When it gets up to 500,I'll give you the answer and we'll split the money.
How about that?
If that's the way you feel, I feel it's my duty under your command
to suggest that we wait until it gets up to 1,000. I think it's...
What if we don't live that long?
-500?  -500 would be good, yes.
Yes, sir.
-Get some sleep, Corporal.  -Yes, sir.
Who's got sulfa powder?
Medic, my buddy's bleeding! He needs a tourniquet.
-Wade.   -Yes, sir?
-See what you can do.   -Yes, sir.
Hold on, fellas. It won't be much longer.
How are we doing here?
Alright. You're doing alright, don't worry about it. The Doc's in town.
Don't worry. The 29th Infantry's breaking through. They'll be here soon.
Has anybody got plasma?
Hey, Captain!
-Soldier,you want to fill me in?  -Yeah.Lieutenant DeWindt.
99th Troop Carrier Squadron carrying in 300th and 307th Glider Infantry.
This one was mine. I was the pilot. Private!
22 men dead. Take care of this one.
I landed there without a scratch, took my co-pilot's head right off.
Who are these people?
The guys we came in with headed off the first night. Haven't seen them since.
In the meantime other guys keep showing up. One, two, six at a time.
Then some officer will come along, patch together a mixed unit, -
and head off to make trouble.
We're looking for a Private Ryan, Baker Company, 506th of the 101st.
You got me. A lot of guys come in and out.
Upham! Check out that squad. See if Ryan's in it.
Yes, sir.
Reiben! Smell that leg, right there. Find out if it's south of cheese.
What?
Hands over your head.
Keep moving!
I'm Jude, you know.
I couldn't pry him out of there. I need a winch.
Yeah.
-Stars.  -Yeah.
Brigadier General Amend. Deputy Commander, 101st.
Some genius had the great idea of welding steel plates onto our deck
to keep the General safe from ground fire,
but they forgot to tell me until just before we were getting airborne.
That's like trying to fly a freight train. OK?
Gross overload. Trim characteristics all shot to hell.
I nearly broke both my arms trying to keep her level.
When we released I cut as hard as I could,
trying to gain some altitude and keep her from stalling.
We came down like a fucking meteor. And this is how we ended up.
The others stopped easy enough, though.
We were just too damn heavy, you know?
The grass was wet. Downward slope and all.
22 guys dead.
-All that for a general?  -One man.
There's a lot of that going around. "FUBAR."
-"FUBAR."  -"FUBAR."
"FUBAR."  -You all got that right.
I looked it up in a German dictionary. "FUBAR"'s not there.
Upham! There are more paratroopers out there.
Find out if one of them is Ryan.
You might want to check this out, sir.
Dog tags. More than I really want to count, sir.
I've covered a lot of bodies, sir.
-Jackson. Start going through those.  -Yes, sir.
I'll help.
-Do you think that little prick's in there?  -If he is,I'm going to find him.
I bet that son of a bitch... I've got money saying he's still alive.
0 bucks says I nail him first. Let's see what we've got in here.
You mugs don't stand a chance. Do you think he's in here?
Just keep looking. Alright.
"Gary lanico", "Ben Rubino", "Mike Cesario"...All the Guineas are buying it.
Come on, it's not the right name! 'Wee Willie Winkie". A buddy of yours.
We've got to find this prick.
Where's this son of a bitch?
Don't mix them up. Keep them in your pile.
How am I supposed to know who we've got?
Why don't you just shut up, Reiben?
Everybody be friends. Cranky there, huh?
-I think I've got a winner.  -What are you talking about?
"Ryan." Ryan?
Take a look at that, Mellis. You're really a genius.
"R-l-E-N-N-E." That's "Rienne" and it's French. Do you know what that means?
It means "nothing". What beats three of a kind?
I got shit here, all guys from New York. You're always bitching.
Do you need a hand? I've got a full house.
I've got you beat. Straight flush.
You're looking at my cards. You're cheating.
Fucking unreal, this guy. Can you read that shit?
Jesus, look at this poor bastard! I guess they're not bulletproof.
I guess not.
I don't like what's between his ears.It's like what's between your legs.
We've got to give him that. That's not bad for you, Jackson.
I've got three of a kind. What the hell are you doing?
The whole goddam Airborne's watching. These aren't poker chips.
Alright. Put them back in there.
He's not here.
Maybe we should split into groups?
Just wander the woods calling his name.
He's bound to hear us sooner or later. Ryan!
That might be a little hard to do, Captain.
Maybe the locals have seen him. Ryan, James Ryan?
Ryan! Anybody know Ryan, 101st Airborne? You know Ryan?
Private James Ryan from lowa? Anybody know a Ryan?
James Ryan! Hey, Joe!
Doesn't Michaelson pal around with a Ryan from C Company?
I think so. Bring him up.
-You know Private Ryan?  -You have to speak up...
You have to speak up, sir! My hearing is not so good!
It comes and goes. A grenade went off right by my head.
-Got it. Do you know Private Ryan?   -Who?
-Private Ryan? James Ryan?  -Jimmy Ryan?
James. James Francis Ryan.
No, no, no. James Francis Ryan.
Give me a pencil. Something to write on.
Quick, a pencil!
Here you are, a small one.
Write this down: "James Francis Ryan? Iowa?"
"Do you know him?" Read the message! Look!
-Yeah, of course I know him.  -Does he know where he is?
Yeah, we missed our dropzone by about 20 miles
and ended up way over by "Bumville" or some damn place.
Him, me and a couple of others were coming here to the rally point.
We ran into a colonel who was gathering up men to go to Ramelle.
Ramelle? To babysit a bridge.
-That's the last I've seen of him.  -Great! Thank you!
-Write "Thank you". Read. Thank you.  -You're welcome!
Assemble on me.
Thank you, Lieutenant.
Ramelle.
We're here. There. Ramelle is on the Merderet River,right here.
Just to the southwest of us.
You know anything about that bridge we just talk about?
Yeah. The target has always been Cherbourg.
We can't push on Paris until we take a deep water port and Rommel knows that.
He's going to try to get his armour across the Merderet River anyway he can.
That way he can hit us in the flank when we make the turn for Cherbourg.
That makes any village on the river with a bridge solid gold real estate.
Let's go.
Captain.
What the hell is that?
A radar site. It's got to be out of action.
Looks like we've got something in that sandbag bunker under the station.
-See it?   -Yeah, that's my guess, too.
-What is it?    -Machine gun, probably MG-42.
-Is that what got those guys?  -Maybe one of them is Ryan.
No, their patches are 82nd, so your luck's not that good.
I don't know how fast you are, but if we detour this way quick and quiet,
the Krauts will never even know we were here.
What I'm trying to say is why don't we just go around the thing?
I hear what you're saying, but we can't go around it.
I'm with Reiben. I mean, we left those 88s.
For the Air Force. They're not going to spend ordnance on one machine gun.
Captain.
We can skip it and still accomplish our mission. This isn't our mission, right?
Is that what you want to do, Mellish?
Leave it here so they can ambush another company?
No, I'm simply saying it's seems an unnecessary risk given our objective.
Our objective is to win the war.
It's just that I don't have a good feeling about this one.
When was the last time you felt good about anything?
Alright. Three runners with suppressing fire.
Mellish. You hook to the right, I'll go up the middle.
Who's going left?
I'll do it.
-I go left.   -Alright.
Upham, switch off with Jackson and you linger in the rear.
We advance and keep pressure on him 'til he has to change out his barrels.
We should be able to hit them from grenade range.
-Maybe I should go up the middle?   -The way you run? I don't think so.
-Maybe I should go left,sir.  -Maybe you should shut up!
Reiben, base of fire.
Mags and clips where you can reach them
and extra grenades for the base runners.
Hill's clear. Four down and dead! Upham!
Grab the gear and get up here! We need water and extra dressing.
Get the morphine out of the medical kit!
Son of a bitch! Get some sulfa on there.
Move my legs up. I got them.
Pour sulfa. Listen to my voice.
You're going to be alright, Doc.
You're fine. You're going on a hospital ship.
More sulfa! Move my legs up.
Put my legs up. I've got them.
You're going to be OK. It's alright, Doc.
Upham, give me your canteen! Come on.
We're going to get you out of here. Put some pressure on it.
Am I shot? How does it look? Give him some morphine.
How does it look? You're going to be OK.
Here comes the morphine.
Am I shot in the spine?
You're OK. Am I shot in the spine?
Lift him up. Move him over.
Put some pressure on. Easy, easy.
It's OK, Doc. It's alright.
Wade, you've got an exit wound. It's in the small of your back.
-How big is the hole?   -It's about the size of an acorn.
It's fine. Put him back.
Put some pressure on it. Put some pressure on it.
Put some pressure on it!
Put some more pressure on it.
Is there anything bleeding worse than the others?
Yeah, right here. Do you know what it is? Right here.
I'll put your hand on it. We got some pressure on there.
That's the one.
Oh, my God! My liver! It's my liver!
Tell us what to do. Tell us how to fix you.
What can we do? Tell us what to do.
I could use a little morphine.
More morphine, sir.
OK. OK.
-Sir? What?   -Give it to him.
Give it to him.
I don't want to die! Here you go, Wade. Here it comes.
Give him another one.
Mama...
Mama.
I want to go home, I want go home.
Mama, Mama, Mama...
Mama, Mama, Mama, Mama...
Reiben, hold him!
Not yet!
First make him mark and cover Wade's body for Grave Detail.
Same thing for the paratroopers down there.
Strip that stuff off him. Check him for intelligence.
Ask this piece of shit if he shot Wade! Ask him!
-Does it matter?   -It does!
Shut up with that filthy pig Latin.
Jackson, are you hit?
It just skinned the arm.
Get it cleaned and dressed. You and Sarge watch the perimeter.
He says, "Please don't shoot." I don't care what he says, Upham.
Sir? Sir, are you going to let them kill him?
This is not right, sir. You can help him with the bodies.
What is happening?
American.
I like American.
Steamboat Willie.
Steamboat Willie. Steamboat Willie. American.
He says he's not finished. That's what you think. Come on.
Please! I like America!
Fancy schmancy! What a cinch!
Go fly a kite! Cat got your tongue! Cool beans!
Betty Boop! What a dish.
Betty Grable. Nice gams.
I say can you see
I say...
Fuck Hitler.
Fuck Hitler!
Sir, he says he's sorry about Wade. He says he's sorry about Wade.
Captain!
Captain, this isn't right. You know this.
He's a prisoner. He surrendered. He surrendered, sir!
Tell him...
to march 1,000 paces in that direction.Then he can take off the blindfold.
He turns himself in to the first Allied patrol.
Are you kidding? We're letting him go?
He's a POW, Reiben. We can't take him with us.
Our guys will pick him up. That was a close shave.
Lucky Strikes.
Take me out to the ball game...
Only if he doesn't get picked up by his own and get thrown back into circulation.
Captain, you just let the enemy go. This is such bullshit.
You all got that right. Bullshit? This is bullshit?
Shooting a prisoner is OK? It's against the rules!
The goddam rules just walked off with your new friend.
But I guess that was the decent thing to do, Captain?
Get your gear. Let's go.
You heard him. Gear up.
The Captain just gave you an order. Yeah.
Like the one he gave to take this machine gun. That was a real doozy.
You're out of line!
That was one hell of a call coming to take this nest,
but what the hell, we only lost one of our guys going for it.
I hope Mama Ryan's really happy knowing that little Jimmy's life
was more important than two of our guys!
But then, we haven't found them, have we?
Hey... Get off me!
Reiben, get up.
Gear up. Fall in.
I'm done with this mission.
Hey! Hey!
Sir... Don't you walk away from your captain!
-Reiben, get back in line!   -No, sir.
I'll spend the rest of my life in the stockade rather than go on.
I'm not going to ask you again. Captain!
This is bullshit! Fall in!
-Are you going to shoot me over Ryan?   -No, because I don't like you.
If he wants to go, just let him go!
Are you letting this happen? Captain! You see this?
Captain. Sir, Ryan's dead.
Bullshit! We have a situation here.
I have a sixth sense. I know it in my bones.
We didn't kill the Kraut. Now you're going to shoot me.
-He's better than you.  -Just do it!
-Put one in my leg...  -I'll shoot you in your big mouth!
Put your money where your mouth is and do it!
You don't know how to shut up.
-Captain, please!  -What's the pool on me up to?
-You are a coward son of a bitch!  -I'm waiting, Sarge.
What's the pool on me up to right now?
What's it up to?
What is it? 300 dollars, is that it?
I'm a schoolteacher.
I teach English Composition...
in this little town called Addley, Pennsylvania.
In the last 11 years, I've been at Thomas Alva Edison High School.
I was the coach of the baseball team in the springtime.
I'll be doggone.
Back home, when I tell people what I do for a living
they think, 'Well, that figures."
But over here, it's...
a big, big mystery.
So, I guess I've changed some.
Sometimes I wonder if I've changed so much
my wife is even going to recognise me whenever I get back to her...
and how I'll ever be able to...
tell her about days like today.
Ryan...
I don't know anything about Ryan. I don't care.
He means nothing to me, it's just a name,
but if going to Ramelle and finding him so he can go home,
if that earns me the right to get back to my wife, then...
...then that's my mission.
You want to leave? You want to go off and fight the war?
Alright.
Alright, I won't stop you. I'll even put in the paperwork.
I just know that with every man I kill, the farther away from home I feel.
by memories of days gone by
In my solitude you taunt me
with memories that never die
I sit in my chair filled with despair
There's no one could be so sad
With gloom everywhere I sit and I stare
I know that I'll soon go mad
Half-track! Cover!
Who's doing the shooting? Who's doing the shooting?
Get ready to move. Take their left flank!
Hold on and make sure they're down.
101st! We're coming out!
That was a recon. element, 2nd SS.
We've been expecting a probe. That must have been it.
Captain Miller, Charlie Company, 2nd Rangers.
Corporal Henderson, Easy Company, 501st.
Ryan, First of 506th. Toynbee, Third of 506th.
-James Francis Ryan?  -Yes,sir.How did you guess that?
-Looks like you got hit pretty hard.  -Yes,sir.Small unit action.
They came in and beat the hell out of us with 88s.
Tell you what. If you're our relief, I'm going to file a complaint.
I wouldn't blame you.
Who's your CO?
It would've been Captain Jennings.
I'm afraid the best we can muster up now is a corporal.
So what are you guys all about?
We're here for him. Ryan.
Me, sir?
James Francis Ryan of lowa?
Yes, sir. Peyton,Iowa, that's correct. What is this about?
Your brothers were killed in combat.
Which ones?
All of them.
On the level?
Yeah, I'm afraid so.
You might want to take some time with this.
If there's someplace you want to go and...
-What's this all about?  -Ryan lost his brothers.
-Which one?  -All of them.
You came all the way out here to tell me that?
You're going home.
Our orders are to bring you back.
Bring me back?
Corporal,I don't mean to leave you more short-handed,but orders are orders.
Any communications about when you will be relieved?
We can't tell. We don't know what's happening south of us.
My orders don't include me abandoning my post.
I understand that, but this changes things.
I don't see that it does, sir.
The Chief of Staff for the US Army says it does.
Our orders are to hold this bridge at all costs.
Our planes in the 82nd have taken out every bridge across the Merderet,
with the exception of two: one at Valognes and this one.
If the Germans take it, we'll have to displace.
Private.It's one thing that your outfit wants to stay,but your party's over here.
I can't leave before the reinforcements are here.
You've got three minutes to get your gear.
-What about them,there's barely...  -Hey,asshole!
Two of our guys already died trying to find you.
-Sir?  -That's right.
-What were their names?  -Irwin Wade and Adrian Caparzo.
Wade and?
Caparzo.
It doesn't make any sense.
It doesn't make any sense, sir. Why do I deserve to go?
Why not any of these guys? They all fought just as hard as me.
Is that what they're supposed to tell your mother
when they send her another folded American flag?
Tell her that when you found me I was here,
and I was with the only brothers that I have left,
and that there was no way I was going to desert them.
I think she'll understand that. There's no way I'm leaving this bridge.
What are your orders?
Sergeant, we have crossed some strange boundary here.
Our world has taken a turn for the surreal.
Clearly, but the question still stands.
I don't know. What do you think?
You don't want to know what I think.
No, Mike, I do.
Part of me thinks the kid's right. What's he done to deserve this?
If he wants to stay here, fine. Let's leave him and go home.
Yeah.
But another part of me thinks, "What if by some miracle we stay
and actually make it out of here?"
Some day we might look back on this and decide that
saving Private Ryan was the one decent thing we pulled out of
this whole godawful, shitty mess.
That's what I was thinking, sir. Like you said, Captain.
We do that, we all earn the right to go home.
Oh, brother...
This is everything.
You've got the.230 calibre machine guns, 17 grenades, 11 Hawkins mines.
You've got two bazookas, but they've only got eight rounds left.
And assorted small arms.
We had a.60 mortar, but an arty round took it out.
Might as well be spit wads if they roll on us with tanks.
Which they're sure to do. What are you thinking, sir?
I'm thinking I'm going to whip around the flanks.
Unless we can draw them up the main road between the buildings,
where all the rubble makes a bit of a bottleneck
-Disable him?   -If we can.
Make a 60-tonne roadblock. Then we've got a fighting chance at her flanks.
Good. Split them up, don't let them mass.
Hit them hard one-on-one, and fall back to the bridge.
Machine gun on the move down here, number two up high to piss on them.
That would be the idea. Jackson!
If we can, I'd like to get you up in that bell tower.
Yes, sir. I'll give you some company.
Some company couldn't hurt. A.30 with about a 1,000 rounds would be OK.
Parker, job opportunity.
It's not the worst idea ever,
but everything depends on getting the tank down the road for us to knock out.
How the hell do you plan on doing that?
He's right. As our colleague from Airborne pointed out
what we've got is a bunch of spit wads.
How do we stop the tank if we get it to commit?
Give it a rabbit to chase.
We could hit the tank in the tracks.
Yeah, but with what?
-We could try a sticky bomb.  -Sticky bomb, sir?
Sir, are you making that up?
No, it's in the field manual. Check it out, if you want to.
We seem to be out of field manuals. Perhaps you could enlighten us.
You have some demolition, don't you? TNT or Composition B?
Plenty. I've got that bridge wired with enough Composition B to blow it twice.
You can spare some, then.
You take a standard GI sock, cram it full with Composition B,
and rig up a simple fuse. Then you coat the whole thing with axle grease.
That way, when you throw it, it should stick.
It's a bomb that sticks. It's a sticky bomb.
Come up with a better way to knock the tracks off a tank, I'm all ears.
This is good. Now we have to surrender our socks!
Haul away.
Select the field of fire. Crossfire with the one in the bell tower.
I can cover 12 to 9 from here.
Easy! I've got her!
Here are the mines.
For being the best we can do,
that forward machine gun is not in a terrible firing position.
And this position right here...
This is the Alamo.
They push us this far, the last man alive blows the bridge.
We've only got a 30-second delay on the fuse, so tell everyone
that if you're last you'd better hurry or you'll not live long.
Captain? Where am I during all this?
Never more than two feet away from me. And that's not negotiable.
I'm going to get some ammo. Come on.
Hey, Upham, listen to me. Yes.
-Are you listening?  -Yes.
We're going to be displacing and falling back like crazy sons of bitches,
so you've got to be Johnny-on-the-spot with the ammo,or we're dead.
-Do you understand?  -Johnny-on-the-spot.
-Yeah. Are you alright?  -Yeah.
When we shipped out of England we got cigarettes
and I said, "No, thank you. I don't smoke."
-Quite a situation, huh?  -Unbelievable.
Yeah. "Fucked-Up Beyond All Recognition", right?
You've got that right.
-"FUBAR"!   -Alright!
Ouch.
Yeah, well... It's going to be a real show, huh?
Yeah, OK.
Take it easy.
"FUBAR."
Who's that singing, sir?
Edith Piaf.
What is she so upset about?
Her lover left her, but she still sees his face everywhere she goes.
That would do it.
"Even life itself only represents you."
"Sometimes I dream that I'm in your arms."
What was that? She sang it before. The chorus.
The chorus.
"And you speak softly in my ear."
"And you say things that make my eyes close."
"And I find that marvellous."
Again, Upham...
...to be honest, I find myself curiously aroused by you.
Marvellous.
It's a really melancholy song. At the beginning of the song she says:
"And then one day you left me and I've been desperate ever since."
"I see you all over the sky, I see you all over the earth."
Any more songs like this, the Krauts won't have to shoot me.
I'm just going to slit my own wrists.
You're a strange bird, Upham.
I'm sorry. It's Edith, you know.
You know what that song reminds me of?
Mrs. Rachel Troubowitz and what she said when I left for Basic.
What? "Don't touch me?"
No. She's our Super's wife.
She comes into my mum's shop to try a few things. She's like a 44 Double E.
Double E? They're massive.
Those are big titties.
I've got her convinced that she's a 42 D. So we're in the dressing room
and she tries to get into this side-cut,silk-ribboned,triple-panel girdle
with the shelf-lift brassiere.
It's beautiful. She's pouring out of this thing.
-Is it tight?  -No, it's beautiful.
She sees me and can tell I've got a hard-on the size of the Statue of Liberty.
She says, "Richard, calm down", and she says,
"Over there, if you see anything that upsets you, if you're scared,"
"I want you to close your eyes and think of these, you understand?"
So I said, "Yes, ma'am."
Are you alright, sir?
Yeah, I'm just keeping the rhythm.
Is it true you were a teacher back home?
-Yes.   -That's something I could never do.
Not with the way me and my brothers treated our teachers. No, sir!
I had a thousand kids like you.
I can't see my brothers' faces.
I've been trying and I can't see their faces at all. Has that happened to you?
You've got to think of a context.
What does that mean?
You don't just think about their faces, you think about something specific,
something you've done together.
When I want to think of home, I think of something specific.
I think of my hammock in the backyard, -
or my wife pruning the rose bushes in a pair of my old work gloves.
This one night, two of my brothers woke me up in the middle of the night.
They said they had a surprise for me.
They took me to the barn up into the loft
and there was my oldest brother Dan
with Alice Jardine!
Picture a girl who just took a nosedive from the ugly tree
and hit every branch coming down!
And Dan's got her shirt off...
So he's trying to get her bra off and all of a sudden Sean screams out
"Danny, you're a young man. Don't do it!"
Alice Jardine hears this and she screams and jumps up
and tries to run out, but she's got her shirt over her head.
She runs into the wall and knocks herself out.
Now Dan is so mad at us. He starts coming after us,
but at the same time Alice is unconscious. He's got to wake her up.
He grabs her by a leg and drags her
and at the same time he picks up a shovel and goes after Sean!
And Sean says, 'Why are you trying to hit me? I just did you a favour!"
This makes Dan more angry. He tries to swing this thing.
He loses his shovel. It goes out of his grasp and hits a kerosene lantern.
The thing explodes. The whole barn almost goes up because of this thing.
That was it, that was the last... Dan went off to Basic the next day.
That was the last night the four of us were together.
That was two years ago.
Oh, my.
Tell me about your wife and those rose bushes.
No. No, that one I save just for me.
Enemy from the east.
He sees two Tiger tanks, two Panzer tanks.
Infantry. 50 plus change.
Disperse! You know what to do. Reiben, get on the rabbit.
Upham, get some cover. Mellish and Henderson, lock and load!
Everybody check your ammo!
-Good luck,Reiben!  -I don't need any luck,I was born lucky!
One in five tracer. Yes, and tracers point both ways.
Why don't you check the head space and she should run.
Upham, hustle up!
Corporal Upham. We don't have a.30 calibre machine gun here.
Either Mister Mellish or Mr Jackson in the bell tower needs that.
Upham! Jackson's fine, turn around to Mellish!
There's a ton of infantry. I don't know if they took the bait, though.
Have you got any more of that?
The Panzers didn't take the bait.
The infantry's moving to the left.
A half-track just went by with about 20 troops.
Mellish, Henderson! Displace!
Do it, now! Light it up! You! Light it!
30 infantry on the right flank. Get over there, find a hole and stop them!
Displace!
Upham!
Clear! OK, go!
Krauts!
Right flank!
Get down, get down!
Upham! Thirty cal, hurry!
Find the Captain, this flank's going to fold!
Traversing! He's still in this fight!
No! Ryan, get down, get down!
Ryan!
Keep your mouth shut Get off me!
-Are you alright?  -Get off of me!
I'm fine too, Captain. Thanks.
Hit them from both sides. Get aboard! Get a grenade in there!
Grenade!
20 mill! 20 mill!
Flak gun, 20 mm. Take it out!
Heavy weapon in defilade below! I ain't got a shot!
Pincer move! Parker! Targets eight o'clock, low!
God grant me strength.
Let's go, displace! Come on!
Cover! Upham, cover!
I'm out of.30 calibre.
Blessed be the Lord my strength, which teaches my hands to war -
and my fingers to fight.
My goodness and my fortress. My high tower and deliverer.
My shield and He in whom I trust.
Here you go, baby.
Parker, get down!
Captain, that 20 mm is killing us.
-We've got to try to flank it somehow.  -Let me get over there for a top shot.
Upham!
Upham, Upham! Upham, ammo, goddammit!
-I'm jammed! Got any.30 calibre?   -I'm out.
Upham. Upham!
Reiben!
I'm out! I need another bandolier. Anybody got a bandolier?
You piece of shit!
Let's stop, let's stop! Listen to me! Stop! No, no, no...
Fuck!
Son of a bitch, son of a bitch!
Son of a bitch!
I'm out! Those.60 rounds...
-We can use them without the tube.   -How?
Fuse-arming wire, set back and heave it!
Panzer schreck!
Go, go!
We're going to the Alamo.
Alamo! Alamo!
We'll take it. You fall back! You be right behind us!
As soon as we're in business.
Displace. Reiben!
Reload!
Alright, go!
We're blowing the bridge! Get off! Off the bridge!
Sarge! Mike, are you alright?
-I just got the wind knocked out of me.  -Let's go!
Take cover, we're going to blow this bridge!
Come on!
Tiger company's coming across the bridge.
Captain, get behind something!
Mike!
Captain, where the hell are you going? Captain, get back here!
Upham!
Hang in there.
Medic!
Medic! We've got a medic?
They're tankbusters, sir. P-51s.
Angels on our shoulders.
What, sir?
James...
Earn this.
Earn it.
"My dear Mrs Ryan."
"It's with a profound sense of joy that I write to inform you"
"that your son, Private James Ryan, is well"-
"and at this moment on his way home from European battlefields."
"Reports indicate that James did his duty in combat"
"with great courage and steadfast dedication"
"even after he was informed of the loss your family has suffered"
"in this great campaign to rid the world of tyranny and oppression."
"I take great pleasure injoining the Secretary of War, "
"the men and women of the US Army, and the citizens of a grateful nation"
"in wishing you good health and many years of happiness with James."
"Nothing, not even the safe return of a beloved son"
"can compensate you or the thousands of other American families"
"who have suffered great loss in this tragic war."
"I might share with you some words"-
"which have sustained me through nights of peril, loss and heartache, "
"and I quote, 'I pray that our heavenly Father"
"may assuage the anguish of your bereavement"
"and leave you only the cherished memory of the loved and lost"
"and the solemn pride that must be yours"
"to have laid a so costly a sacrifice upon the altar of freedom."
"Abraham Lincoln."
"Yours very sincerely and respectfully,"
"George C. Marshall. General, Chief of Staff."
My family is with me today. They wanted to come with me.
To be honest with you, I wasn't sure how I would feel coming back here.
Every day, I think about what you said to me that day on the bridge.
I've tried to live my life the best I could.
I hope that was enough.
I hope that at least in your eyes...
l've earned what all of you have done for me.
James.
"Captain John H. Miller."
-Tell me I have led a good life. -What?
Tell me I'm a good mess.
You are.